Guide to the William Bryans Papers MC 29
New York University Archives
William Bryans Papers
1892-1954
MC 29
New York University Archives
0.25 linear feet
This collection documents the history of the College of Engineering as written by a New York University faculty member. Bryans served both as Assistant Dean and Professor of Engineering Mechanics at the College of Engineering in his four-decade career at the University. The collection contains manuscripts of and photographs from two separate histories of the College written by Bryans.
Bryans, William Remington, 1884-1974
Related Materials
Charles H. Snow Papers, 1917 - 1943
Records of the Student Army Training Corps 1916 - 1921
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are arranged by manuscript and further by format.
New York University College of Engineering in World War II
Thirty-Eight, Thirty-Eight, Twenty-Four, or Three Epochs in the First One Hundred Years of Engineering
Scope and Content Note
This collection documents the historical research of an NYU alumnus who went on to serve the University as both a professor and an administrator. The collection contains manuscripts for two works on the history of the College of Engineering as well as photographs that illustrate each manuscript.
Biography of William Bryans
Born in New York City, William R. Bryans (1884-1974) attended Manual Training High School in Brooklyn from 1895-1902 before attending New York University. He graduated NYU with a B.S. in Mechanical Engineering in 1906 and achieved the degree of Mechanical Engineer in 1909. Less than a year after graduation, Bryans took his first job at New York University, where he continued to work for over four decades in many capacities, including as a Professor of Engineering Mechanics, the Secretary of Faculty, and Assistant Dean. In 1949 he was named Professor Emeritus and was granted an Honorary Doctorate in Engineering.
During his academic career Bryans published several papers on the mechanics of materials and engineering education. He also authored two books, Concise Mechanics of Materials and Mechanics of Internal Work in 1928 and Resistance of Materials in 1931.
Bryans was a member of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers, the Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the American Association of University Professors, Iota Alpha, and the NYU Faculty Club. During World War I, Bryans served as Assistant Director in charge of instruction for the Student Army Training Corps from 1917-1918.
New York University. College of Engineering.; Snow, Charles H., (Charles Henry), 1863-1957; Manuscripts (document genre); New York University |x History.; New York University. School of Engineering.; Photographs.; World War, 1939-1945.
- New York University College of Engineering in World War II
  - Manuscript
    - New York University College of Engineering in World War II Manuscript, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs
    - New York University College of Engineering in World War II Photographs, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Thirty-Eight, Thirty-Eight, Twenty-Four or Three Epochs in the First One Hundred Years of Engineering
  - Manuscript
    - Thirty-Eight, Thirty-Eight, Twenty-Four or Three Epochs in the First One Hundred Years of Engineering Manuscript Chapters 1-7, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Thirty-Eight, Thirty-Eight, Twenty-Four or Three Epochs in the First One Hundred Years of Engineering Manuscript Chapters 8-12, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs
    - Thirty-Eight, Thirty-Eight, Twenty-Four or Three Epochs in the First One Hundred Years of Engineering Photographs, 1892-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)